[Music]
consider a right triangle with legs of
length a
b and hypotenuse of length c
the in circle of this triangle is the
largest circle contained in the triangle
it is tangent to each of the three sides
the radius r of this circle is called
the in radius of the triangle
the inradius can be used to decompose
the triangle into four triangles and a
square as demonstrated
if we glue a second rotated copy of this
triangle to the original along the
hypotenuse we end up with a rectangle
decomposed into eight triangles and two
squares
we can then arrange the pieces of this
rectangle dissection to form a different
rectangle
[Music]
from the decomposition we can see that
this new rectangle has length given by a
plus b
plus c
and the width of the rectangle is given
by the in radius r
because the areas of these two
rectangles must be equal
we can equate the areas to see that a
times b
must be equal
to r times
a plus b plus c
but then we can use this equality
to find that r
is equal
to a times b divided by a plus b plus c
giving us a formula for the n radius of
a right triangle in terms of its side
lengths
but that's not all
we can do more the four triangles from
the original decomposition
tell us extra information
the leg of one triangle is a minus r and
the leg of the other is b minus r
but these two legs side by side create
the hypotenuse of the triangle so that c
is equal to a minus r
plus
b minus r
we can again use this equation to solve
for r
and we'll see that r is equal to a plus
b minus c all divided by two
we have found two formulas for the n
radius of the right triangle in terms of
the side lengths
[Music]
you